Writing a resume and a cover letter

Managers are short of time . Make them win time :

A resume or CV (Curriculum Vitae) is a way to provide enough information about yourself to convince a recruiting agent to meet you.

What is a resume?

A summary of relevant job experience and education for your job search

- -Mention your qualifications. Start with the most recent one. Include course title, subject studied and dissertation topic if relevant.
- -all useful skills should be included :Computer literacy,computing programmes and softwares,ability to drive,language fluency...
- -Employment and work history. Start with the most recent one ,give indications of your professional skills (apprenticeship)
- " Able to demonstrate a methodical approach to programming and software testing.
- " Have a proven track record of analytical problem solving skills.
- -Mention the activities where you have leadership or responsibility, or which involve you in relating to others in a team
- " Ability to produce technical reports to a high standard both in terms of technical content, presentation and written English.
- " Have enthusiasm, good communication skills and the ability to work effectively in a multi-disciplinary team.
- -If you have published any articles, jointly or by yourself, give details.

LM

- -If you have been involved in any type of of volunteer work, give details.
- -Give two names of referees :one from your place of study and one from any work situation you have had. Make sure that the referees are willing to give you a reference!

Ten tips for a successful resume

- **1.Keep it concise**: a resume should be no more than 2 sides of A4 paper. Recruiters spend an average of 8 seconds reviewing a resume, so keep it punchy ,to the point and save the details for the interview.
- 2.Adapt your resume to each job you are applying for :research the company and use the job ad to assess exactly which skills you should signpost and which aren't so relevant.
- **3.Include a personal statement**: use a brief personal statement to the work history, to the specific company and role.
- **4.Don't leave gaps**. If the recruiter spots something is missing, he is unlikely to give you the benefit of the doubt.
- 5-Update your resume regularly, even if you are actively seeking a job, every time something significant occurs in your career, record it so nothing slips through the memory sieve.
- **6-Ensure it is mistake-free** :use a spell-checker and ask someone else to proof your work.
- **7-Tell the truth**, never tell blatant lies. Many companies check the facts and any inconsistency in your story will be ruthlessly probed at the interview stage.

- 8-Back up your achievements with figures or concrete examples: « championed implementation of a new software which increased productivity by 10% »
- **9-Spend time formatting your resume** :use bullet points and keep sentences short, make sure the lay out is easy on the eye.
- 10-Keywords are vital in ensuring recruiters can find out if you've uploaded your resume to a recruitment website. Universally understood job titles and sector buzzwords will help a search engine pick out your resume from the pile.

Differences between the US and the UK

https://www.cvcorrect.com/guide/cv-differences-usa-uk

Paying attention to the minute differences between British and American curricula can ensure a successful application.

A resume is preferred in the US and also Canada. Americans and Canadians would only use a CV when they were applying for a job abroad, or if they were looking for an academic or research-oriented position.

A CV is preferred in the UK but also in countries that have more in common with the UK such as Ireland, Australia and New Zealand.

Spelling

When you compose the CV, ensure the correct use of language as a distinction is made between American and British English. Use English according to the country where you are applying for a job. Differences lie in the vocabulary, the grammar and the spelling. For example, a lawyer in British English is the 'solicitor', but in American English, he is the 'attorney'.

Small differences in spelling should not become pitfalls for you. In British English, one writes 'programme', but in American English, it is 'program'. In American English,

one says 'analyze', whereas in British English, one writes 'analyse'.

With hindsight, one may add that the above distinction is getting blurred in many cases, as dictionaries like the Oxford English Dictionary now classify 'realize' as a primary British English spelling, while 'realise' appears as the word's medieval, secondary spelling. The rule also applies to words like 'dramatize', 'anatomize' and all verbs ending in '-ize'. However, 'analyse' is an exception and so is 'catalyse'. In American spelling convention, they are spelt 'analyze' and 'catalyze'. We recommend consulting a good British English dictionary to clear confusion regarding this.

Title/layout

In terms of the title and the layout, there are fundamental differences between CVs in British English and those in American English. In the UK, the document is called a CV (Curriculum Vitae) and the title is placed as a heading on the résumé. In the US, it is called 'Personal Résumé' or 'Curriculum Vitae'. The résumé for a position in the private sector, summarizes briefly the most important work-related activities for the job within one page. The detailed CV is used in the US when applying for academic professions and jobs in the field of research.

Personal details

In the American CV, the prospective employer does not care about your date of birth. However, in the British résumé, it is compulsory to state your date of birth and, sometimes, even your nationality. But you should mention the latter, only if the information is important for the

employer because of work visa issues or other such formalities.

Career objective or personal statement

In the American CV, the career objective or personal statement is part of the curriculum vitae as well as in the British CV.

Final grades

For an application in the UK, it is important to translate your grades into the British grading system. You can find online tables to help you with the translation.

Interning

There are several words that typically crop up on a CV or resume that differ between the US and the UK. In America the word 'internship' is used, whereas in the UK this is typically called a 'work placement' or 'training period'. If you have been an 'intern' in the US, that means you have been a 'trainee' in the UK.

We hope this has helped to clear up some confusion and that you have good luck in your job search!

References

In the American CV, it is important to include references. In the British CV, however, references are listed only if explicitly requested in the job description. Otherwise, it is

LM

sufficient to mention that references can be provided on request.

Picture

British and American CVs do not require a passport photo. But there is a crucial difference between the two countries in this respect: Your application is immediately rejected in the US if you choose to pass along a photo nevertheless. Anti-discrimination laws in the US are very sharp and your future employer may be unwilling to put himself in a position where he could be exposed to the accusation that he preferred you on the grounds of nationality, colour or religion.

In the UK, a photo lacks such far-reaching consequences. Nevertheless, you should not send any image without a corresponding request.

We hope this has helped to clear up some confusion and that you have good luck in your job search!

LM

Andrew Thomas BSc (Hons)

<u>Experienced Software Developer</u> <u>First Class Computer Science Graduate</u>

.

Profile

A highly motivated first-class Computer Science graduate with a keen interest in technology and business as well as a high level of experience in software development. Consistently working to the highest professional standards drawing on experience and a wide range of technical expertise. Additionally an effective team player with excellent communication and organisational skills combined with a desire to succeed.

Achievements

- Gaining a first class honours degree.
- Winning the **Accenture** Strategy Award for Scientists and Engineers.
- Passing the Institute of Advanced Motorists (IAM) Advanced Driving Test.
- Being top student on the Computer Science with Business Management course at the **University of Birmingham** for three years running.

Education

- BSc (Hons) Class 1 in Computer Science with Business Management, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, UK.
- A & AS Level, Newport Free Grammar School, Essex
- GCSE, Newport Free Grammar School, Essex

Employment History

- Software Developer at Autonomy Systems Ltd, now part of HP
- Operations Development at Autonomy Systems Ltd, now part of HP
- Web and Systems Developer at Toucan Internet LLP
- Part time Developer at Bell Press Printers Ltd

IT Skills

- Web programming in HTML, CSS, JavaScript/jQuery, PHP and MySQL
- Programing and development in Java.
- Some experience of Node.js.

LM

- Unit testing with tools such as JUnit, Mockito and PowerMock.
- IntelliJ IDEA, NetBeans and Eclipse IDEs for Java development.
- Experience of C/C++, XML and Linux Shell Scripting.
- Agile software development methodologies, including being Scrum Master.
- Microsoft Office.
- Adobe Dreamweaver, Photoshop and Flash.
- Various operating systems including Windows XP/Vista/7, Mac OS X and Ubuntu/CentOS Linux.

Skills, Hobbies & Interests

- Driving holder of a full driving licence and an IAM Advanced Driver.
- Skiing.
- Playing badminton and squash.
- Gadgets and technology.

References available upon request

LM

US Resumé (sample)

May Trix 888-888-8881 | mtrix@andrew.cmu.edu

OBJECTIVE:

An internship or research opportunity that will allow me to utilize my problem solving skills and attention to detail to further develop my abilities in the field of computer science.

EDUCATION

CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY B.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE Pittsburgh, PA | Expected May 2018

SKILLS Java • Python • C • SML • HTML5 • CSS • Django • Android • LATEX• Git Data structures • Software design patterns

COURSEWORK

Parallel and Sequential Data Structures and Algorithms Introduction to Computer Systems Software System Construction Great Theoretical Ideas in Computer Science Web Application Development Principles of Imperative Computation Principles of Functional Programming

LINKS Github:// sumkit LinkedIn:// summerkitahara

EXPERIENCE

CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY, HUMAN-COMPUTER INTERACTION INSTITUTE |

RESEARCH ASSISTANT February 2016 - Present | Pittsburgh, PA

- Make Android and web apps for NavCog, a tool that uses sensors, computer vision, and crowdsourcing to help blind people move in spaces. Target crowdsourcing effort to create 3-D models of buildings and maintain sensors. June 2015 August 2015 | Pittsburgh, PA
- Led 3 person team developing mobile and wear apps for Chorus, a webbased crowdsourcing conversational assistant. Has text to speech and speech to text capabilities. Uses Yelp Search and Yahoo APIs.
- Made a natural language processor tool to be added to Chorus web application.

LM

BUSINESS GOLF ACADEMY | SOCIAL MEDIA MANAGER May 2015 - Present | Pittsburgh, PA

• Manage the social media presence for BGA, which encourages women to use golf to advance their careers. Tripled Twitter followers

PROJECTS

UMBRELLA | LEAD ANDROID DEVELOPER, GIT REPO MANAGER February 2016

- App uses crowdsourcing to fight gender-based violence and the bystander effect. Bluetooth-based messaging where users anonymously post situation. BUDGIE | LEAD ANDROID DEVELOPER, GIT REPO MANAGER September 2015
- App to manage and categorize expenses. Implements Microsoft's Oxford Opitcal Character Recognition API. Pie charts show spending distribution.

ACTIVITIES WOMEN'S VARSITY GOLF TEAM | CAPTAIN (2014-PRESENT) August 2014 – Present | Pittsburgh, PA

- Won Thomas B. Craig & LaVerne Craig Tartan Award 2015-2016 (Most Valuable Player), University Athletic Association All Association First Team, Eastern College Athletic Conference Rookie of the Month Division III, University Athletic Association Women's Golf Athlete of the Week (3 times) Student Athlete Advisory Council | September 2014 May 2015 WOMEN@SCS | MENTOR September 2014 Present | Pittsburgh, PA
- "Big sister" in the Big Sister/Little Sister mentoring program. THE FIRST TEE OF PITTSBURGH | VOLUNTEER GOLF INSTRUCTOR September 2014 Present | Pittsburgh, PA

ACTIVITIES:

CMU KGB, Fall 2014-Present. Varsity High School Cross Country, Fall 2012-Fall 2013 (Team Captain, 2013). Varsity High School Track, Spring 2012-Spring 2014 Junior Engineering Technical Society, 2012-2014.

Reference available upon request

LM

- 1) I wish they ...apply for the job. a- can b-will c-didn't
- 2) What...you do if you...me?
 a-did ..were b-do..are c-would...were
- 3) What ...done if you...in advance ?
 a-would you..had know b-would you have..had known
 c-would you...you knew
- 4) I...a training period in computing development. a-held b-carried out c-carried on
- 5) I'm so eager ...work for them. a-at b-to c-for
- 6) I was granted a ...during my studies which helped me considerably.

 a-scholarship b-fee c-benefit
- 7) I think I could be fully...in this project. a-comitted b-committed c-committed
- 8) This is the kind of ...I would like to get. a-internship b-entertainment c-working placement
- 9) If only I could get an interview!

 A-can b-will c-could
- 10)Don't forget to add your ... at the end of your résumé!

LM

- a-references b-credentials c-relatives
- 11)I wish you...him.Now it's too late.
- a-hadn't trust b-didn't trust c-hadn't trusted
- 12) What are your career...?
- a-plans b-prospects c-projects
- 13)He has a good...of foreign languages.
- a-handling b-command c-mastering
- 14)I'd rather ...than do something i don't like.
- a-not work b-not to work c-to not work
- 15)She applied because she knew they wanted to fill a... .
- a-vacancy b-gap c-hole